no
no no no no no no no no no no no no no
no no no
so we have a question on um
five entrances and um
it starts with a quote from a suta
that just well generic description of
the hindrances from the sutta saying
these five things are obstructions
hindrances that encircle the mind weaken the wisdom
that encircle the mind weaken the wisdom
what five central desires is an
obstruction it's a hindrance in circling the mind
it's a hindrance in circling the mind
weakness of the wisdom ill will
sloth and oprah restlessness and remorse
and doubt
is an obstruction a weakener of wisdom
these are the five obstructions
hindrances encircles of the mind
weakness of the wisdom
and then the
so the question is then says uh
previously i was addicted to getting
pleasure by following whatever felt good
which only led me to agitation and
depression fortunately i made the effort
to investigate my situation and by doing
so i gained perspective on it seeing the
danger in my choices that led to my
addictions and subsequent depression
i then made effort in cultivating virtue
and restraint which led to contentment
but also
to gaining an even higher perspective
i'm now able to see certain bad mental
states that i'm addicted to or simply
cannot stop indulging in when they
appear specifically the five hindrances
i welcome lust in dal jengar inclined
towards distraction play with my
restlessness and wrestle with confusion
so
although i do not lose my previously
cultivated level of perspective by
becoming unrestrained and unvirtuous i'm
still struggling to attain a higher
perspective due to my subtle involvement
with these five obstructive mental
states how can i cleanse my mind of
these things what am i missing
so
yeah so when the practice reaches the
stage of um
you recognizing the five hindrances for
what they are
um but then at the same time not giving
in to unvirtuous behavior and losing
your restraint
that's uh that's pretty much the
indicator where you should really be
seeking some
some
stricter forms of seclusion and
isolation because
uh by increasing solitude again not not
as a rule of thumb it doesn't mean that
whenever you increase solitude you'll
get to see the subtle states no
because that can be done for the wrong
reasons and prior development as we
often speak about like there is an order
of development the gradual training
requires developing
the gradual developing in a certain
order so uh
solitude as as a as a next step in your
development comes pretty much after as
the buddha said you have been
established in virtue established in
sense restraint established in the right
view and so on
because yes as the as the question
points out it's they are obviously um
higher to not indulge with because they
are on the level of the mind their
mental state deeply rooted mental
pressures you know pressure sensuality
pressure of ill will
and if
if that person is still living in the
environment that is
at the same time
uh bombarded with uh with with other
sort of sense objects and pulls and
distractions and duties and requirements
and so on you you simply won't have
enough enough composure
and enough strength to endure things on
that mental level without you know
either dismissing it or giving in to it
and so on
so that's why surmounting the
four in order to surmount the five
hindrances then the secluded lifestyle
is is is necessary and and that's
exactly why then the genre would follow
from there
and goes same in the in the gradual
training um the weather says basically
that once you know having been established in
once you know having been established in
sense restraint
virtue watchfulness
watchfulness
not giving in not breaking the precepts
purifying your mind of the mental states
in other words you know not giving in to
bad behaviors and bad cultivations then
you can go to solitude
and then that solid should be bear fruit
towards the complete uh seclusion from
these on wholesome states even
internally and that's then the
description carries on the first john
and the second jhana and so on in the
suttas so
so
if if this is the the factual state of
affairs as in if whoever asked this is
clear about
their level of progression and this is
uh accurate
then uh then yeah uh pretty much the
only thing you specifically the the
person who asked the question needs to
do is uh
try and uh spend prolonged periods of
time in seclusion and then when
when these deeply rooted pressing mental
states hindrances the encirclers of the
mind and weakness of the wisdom arise
well there will be nothing else taking
away you know your energy your time
distracting you and you will be able to
then apply the same principle towards
those mental states principle of not
welcoming not delighting not running
away not distracting from and certainly
not acting out of
and in that seclusion you can endure
those things and the more you endure it
then the um
the um
basically the uh
the less fuel is being provided
for those states to to return at the at
the in the same intensity or at the same
in the same intensity or at the same
strength
so that's why it will take time it's not
like okay and i'll go to seclusion and
boom hindrances disappear no you have to
be living and dwelling in seclusion and
uh preferring seclusion in order to do
the work that now you recognize needs
doing addressing the five hindrances on
the level of the mental state
so yes for somebody that might not take
that long but for for other people
it can it can take um practically a long
time which which doesn't you know it
doesn't matter how long it takes
basically it's it's the worth it's the
work worth doing so um
so then the the next step would be
seclusion and then um
that would result in that higher
perspective or like a
let's say higher levels of disowning of
your own mental state correctly
uh without you know
dismissing them or just kind of applying
the theoretical view that oh this is not
mine this is another you basically need
to have endured
the the mental hindrances long enough
without acting out of them
endure their pressure and do their pain
and do their discomfort and do their
dart burning amber all these
descriptions that the buddha gave and
then you will realize this is not worth
holding this is not worth possessing
whatever they're pointing at to for me
you know to have or to deal with it's
not worth engaging and that's how i free
myself from the burning embers of
sensuality or you know the pressured
pressure the rabbit kind of anger and
whatever else kind of emotions might
take over the mind and as for you know i
our more general audience that uh
that's equally sort of interested in
overcoming hindrances uh just to
emphasize again it's important to
recognize that there is a certain order
of development
and although yes it would be great if
you could just you know enter ghana here
and now and then
deal with everything else that's not how
it works that's not how the gradual
training work works and that's not what
the suttas describe
so
by all means
strive to approve the hindrances but you
need to recognize that in order to even
start seeing the hindrances correctly as
we said in
a number of previous talks
you need to recognize that
first and foremost your behavior your
sense restraint
your watchfulness need to have been
thoroughly thoroughly developed um
in face of that you know pain and
pressure of centrality and ill will and
external circumstances
um so
depending on what's
or you know what stage of the gradual
training a person might be
uh the uh the practice the practice is
then either to develop virtue
unshakable virtues seeing the danger in
the slightest fault
recognizing the intentions behind your
actions as the root of the you know what
defines wholesome as wholesome and
holstmas and wholesome taking
responsibility for it which then results
in watchfulness and then
the the
pressures of the hindrances which are
exhibited in that broadest mental sense
are is going to become more and more uh
discernible more and more obvious
and and then you can actually address it
on that level without needing to act out
of it without needing to resist it try
to outrun it and so on
so if a person through self-honesty
discovers that their virtue still hasn't
been you know thoroughly developed they
still break it sense restraint they
still give in
then again yeah be honest about it and
recognize that
although you have a burning desire and a
strong determination inspiration to deal
with the hindrances you won't be dealing
with them until these
prerequisites are addressed
but then yeah
if you address the prerequisites
you will kind of be dealing with the
hindrances even if you don't necessarily
want to specifically so like even in
this this original question the fact
that this person recognizes the the
pressures on the level of these bad
mental states
that uh that you know that are affecting
him on that level
but he's still not breaking the virtue
or losing the restraint means okay no
that's already a beginning of correctly
addressing the hindrances
um you know the fact that they were able
to ask a question how do i cleanse my
mind of specifically
the hindrances on this level
you know without breaking virtue without
losing sensory strength means like okay
so
the phenomenon of that the width of the
hindrances the the domain of the
hindrances is becoming clearer
and if you really want to
feel that domain that pressure properly
to the full extent and learn how not to
act out of it that's where the seclusion
comes and it will amplify it will
clarify it it will unclutter it and it
will be felt in its like a full extent
um so
yeah it's not going to be pleasant but
how unpleasant is i often say how
unpleasant it will be
depends on you know how addicted to
sensuality and acting out available you
were before so
one way or the other you will have to go
through some withdrawals and not acting
out of that pressure on the level of the
of the mental uh hindrances
and then yes if uh like um you know if
if sometimes that that pressure gets it
just gets too much or if the solitude
gets interrupted
that's fine that work
is not automatically undone
for as long as you don't break the
virtue and become unrestrained for as
long as you don't know too far the other
way so if something you know demands you to
so if something you know demands you to
sort of
come out of your solitude and deal with
and so on you will be able to address it
and then go back to it and pick up where
you left pretty much
although you know the hindrance of doubt
might make you doubt that and make you
wanna break the precepts and everything else
break the precepts and everything else
for the sake of dealing with hindrances
again but again person who has been able
to recognize the hindrances on the level
of the mental states for what they are
will see this as a doubt they're just
trying to trick you
so as long as the virtue remains intact
seeing the danger in the slightest fault
being mindful of your intentions
even if you come and go out of solitude
uh the work that you did before in that
solution is not automatically lost so
when you go back you pick up you pick up
pretty much
the level you left it at